Morning.
おはよう:good morning, おはようございます:good morning
(麻衣)おはよう｡
(咲太)おはようございます｡
Good morning.
眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|, 一睡[いっすい]:wink of sleep/snooze/doze
眠れなかったの？
一睡もできませんでした｡
You couldn't sleep?
Not a wink.
Are you implying that it's my fault?
私のせいだって言いたいの？
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 神経[しんけい]:nerve|nerves/sensitivity, 図太い[ずぶとい]:bold/shameless/cheeky, 熟睡[じゅくすい]:sound sleep
麻衣さんは神経図太すぎ｡
よく熟睡できましたね｡
You've got nerves of steel.
I can't believe you slept like a log.
子ども[こども]:child/children, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu), 撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming, あちこち:here and there/all around|to get things in the wrong order (back to front)
子どもの頃から 撮影で
あちこちに行ってたから｡
Well, I've traveled for shoots since I was a child.
隣[となり]:neighbor (neighbour)/next to (esp. living next door to), 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
それに 咲太が隣に寝てるくらい
なんともないの｡
Also, I think nothing of having you sleeping next to me.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 機会[きかい]:chance/opportunity
いいことを聞いたので
次の機会には
That's good to hear.
I think I'll play some pranks next time.
いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), いたずら:mischief/prank|pastime, いたずら:useless/vain/aimless
いろいろと いたずらしようと
思います｡
As if you have the nerve.
度胸[どきょう]:courage/bravery/pluck, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
そんな度胸なんてないくせに｡
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch, 学校[がっこう]:school
藤沢まで戻って
お昼から学校へ行くんでしょ？
We're going back to Fujisawa and heading to school for the afternoon, right?
準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, なさる:to do
準備するから
ちょっと外に出てなさい｡
Step outside for a bit and let me get ready.
一夜[いちや, ひとや]:one night/all night/overnight, 明ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, やっぱり:too/also|still, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe
《一夜明けても
やっぱり麻衣さんは
It's the next day now,
but it looks like I'm still the only one
who can see Mai-san.
以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
僕以外の誰の目にも
見えていないようだ》
Episode 3: A World without You Alone
I asked yesterday, and they said it'd be fine.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely
昨日聞いたらさ
全然大丈夫だって言うんだよ｡
どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly
いつもどおりだよな｡
It's all the same as usual, right?
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 目に入る[めにはいる]:to catch sight of/to come into view/to happen to see
麻衣さんのことが
目に入ってないのか
Are they simply not taking notice of you,
or can they really not see you?
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
本当に見えてないのか｡
I'll go check my class.
教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school
教室見てくる｡
(理央)梓川｡
Azusagawa.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 知らせ[しらせ]:news/word|omen
悪い知らせだよ｡
Bad news.
Everyone else may have forgotten about Sakurajima-senpai.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
私たち以外 桜島先輩のことを
忘れているかもしれない｡
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
少なくとも
国見は覚えていなかった｡
Kunimi didn't remember her, at least.
Seriously?
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ﾎﾝﾄか？
(朋絵)へぇ そうなんだ｡
Oh, really?
It's you.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday
昨日の…｡
あ…｡
Oh...
You remember Sakurajima-senpai, right?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 桜[さくら, サクラ]:cherry tree|decoy|hired applauder|
なぁ 桜島先輩 知ってるよな？
え？ 桜…？
Huh? Sakura what?
Sakurajima Mai, in third year.
桜[さくら, サクラ]:cherry tree|decoy|hired applauder|, 島[しま]:island|territory (of a prostitute, organized crime gang, etc.)/turf, 島[とう]:Island|insula/island, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
３年の桜島麻衣先輩だ｡
(玲奈)ちょっと 朋絵…｡
Hey, Tomoe...
Why's the hospitalization
incident guy talking to you?
病院[びょういん]:hospital, 送り[おくり]:seeing off|funeral|escapement, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
(日南子)病院送りの先輩が
なんで？
Don't ask me.
え… わかんないよ｡
And who's this Sakurawhatever-senpai?
サクラ:cherry tree/cherry blossom, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
(亜矢)ｻｸﾗなんとか先輩って？
行こう｡
Let's go.
How the hell could you forget?
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, 芸能人[げいのうじん]:performer/entertainer/celebrity, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
なんで 忘れてんだ
芸能人の桜島先輩だぞ！
I'm talking about Sakurajima-senpai, the actress!
おい おい！
Wait...
Hey!
心当たりがある[こころあたりがある]:to have an idea/to have a clue
１つだけ心当たりがある｡
There's one likely reason I can think of.
Get any sleep last night?
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, 一睡[いっすい]:wink of sleep/snooze/doze
昨日の夜は寝たか？
一睡もしてない｡
Not a wink.
一睡[いっすい]:wink of sleep/snooze/doze
私も一睡もしてない｡
Me neither.
結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition
(理央)ただの
結果でしかないけど
I know hindsight is twenty-twenty and all,
but that may be why we remember her.
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
理由は そこにあると思う｡
そこって 寝てないことにか？
Because we haven't slept, you mean?
観測[かんそく]:observation/survey/measurement, 理論[りろん]:theory, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
前にした 観測理論の話は
覚えてる？
Do you remember what I said
about the observation theory before?
猫[ねこ, ネコ]:cat|shamisen|geisha||, 猫[ねこま]:cat
ｼｭﾚﾃﾞｨﾝｶﾞｰの猫｡
Schrödinger's cat.
I've always found it absurd,
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, バカげる:to look foolish
正直 ﾊﾞｶげてるとは思ってたけど
目の当たり[まのあたり]:just before one's eyes/in one's presence/personally, 寒気[さむけ, かんき]:chill/the shivers|cold, 走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||
こうして目の当たりにすると
寒気が走るよ｡
but seeing it in action like this
sends chills down my spine.
思春期[ししゅんき]:puberty, 症候群[しょうこうぐん]:syndrome
思春期症候群に？
違う｡
What, Puberty Syndrome?
No.
思春期[ししゅんき]:puberty, 症候群[しょうこうぐん]:syndrome, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents)
(理央)思春期症候群なんてものが
起きる前から
The fact that she was treated like she was invisible in school even before all of this.
学校[がっこう]:school, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 扱う[あつかう]:to deal with (a person)|to deal with (a problem)|to operate (e.g. a machine)||
あの人が学校の中で
空気のように扱われていたことに｡
私自身[わたしじしん, わたくしじしん]:myself, 空気を読む[くうきをよむ]:to read the situation/to sense the mood
私自身も 空気を読んで
Even I went with the flow,
and despite how abnormal it was that
everyone was subconsciously ignoring her,
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 無自覚[むじかく]:unaware or unmindful of/unconsciousness, 無視[むし]:disregarding/ignoring
みんなが桜島先輩を
無自覚に無視してる
異常[いじょう]:strangeness/abnormality/disorder, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 疑問[ぎもん]:question/problem/doubt, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|, 受け入れる[うけいれる]:to accept/to receive/to agree
異常な状況を
疑問も抱かず 受け入れていた｡
I internalized it without
stopping to think about it.
If anything, one could only do this
if they didn't stop to think about it.
逆[ぎゃく]:reverse|converse (of a hypothesis, etc.)|inverse (function), 逆[さか]:inverse/reverse, 疑問[ぎもん]:question/problem/doubt
逆に 疑問に思わないから
できるんだろ｡
糸口[いとぐち]:thread end|beginning|clue
でも だからこそ 糸口は
But that's exactly why I feel like the key to resolving this is within our school.
学校[がっこう]:school, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
この学校の
空気にあるように思える｡
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 学校[がっこう]:school, 観測[かんそく]:observation/survey/measurement
桜島先輩は 学校の誰からも
観測されておらず
Sakurajima-senpai isn't being observed by anyone at school,
destabilizing her state of existence.
存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 確定[かくてい]:decision/settlement|definition, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
存在が確定していない｡
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 学校[がっこう]:school
桜島先輩にとって
この学校こそが
To her, this entire school is Schrödinger's box.
猫[ねこ, ネコ]:cat|shamisen|geisha||, 猫[ねこま]:cat, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 箱[はこ, ハコ]:box|car (of a train, etc.)|shamisen case||
猫を入れた箱なんだよ｡
認識[にんしき]:recognition/awareness/perception, 観測[かんそく]:observation/survey/measurement
認識と観測が
ｷｰになっているのであれば
If observation and cognizance are playing a key role,
意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|, 睡眠[すいみん]:sleep
人の意識が働かない睡眠が
then sleep, a state of unconsciousness, can indeed make one forget about her.
記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, なくす:to lose something|to get rid of, きっかけ:chance/start/cue
記憶をなくす
きっかけになっているという
考え方[かんがえかた]:way of thinking, 納得[なっとく]:consent/assent|understanding
考え方は 私なりに納得はできる｡
That makes a lot of sense to me.
それって つまり…｡
Wait, you mean...
If I'd fallen asleep last night,
I would've forgotten about her too?
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|, 今頃[いまごろ]:about this time
昨日の夜 もし眠っていたら
僕も今頃…｡
Something the matter?
どうかした？
いえ…｡
No.
Don't you have work today?
バイト:work (esp. part time or casual)
今日はﾊﾞｲﾄなんでしょ？
でも…｡
But...
Don't ignore your responsibilities.
きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, なさる:to do, 平気[へいき]:coolness/calmness|all right
そういうのは きちんとしなさい
私なら平気だから｡
No need to worry about me.
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future
それじゃ また明日ね｡
See you tomorrow, then.
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe
《誰も麻衣さんを見ていない｡
Nobody sees Mai-san.
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 観測[かんそく]:observation/survey/measurement
麻衣さんは 誰にも
観測されていなくて
She's not being observed by anyone,
which is destabilizing her state of existence.
存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 定まる[さだまる]:to become settled/to be fixed
存在が定まっていなくて
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear
だから 消えてゆく｡
That's why she's disappearing.
認識[にんしき]:recognition/awareness/perception, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
誰にも認識してもらえなければ
If no one recognizes you,
you may as well not exist at all.
この世[このよ]:this world/the present life (in contrast to the land of the dead), 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
この世に存在してないのと
同じだから…》
学校[がっこう]:school, 発端[ほったん]:origin/genesis/opening
でも 学校が
発端だっていうなら
But if our school really is the cause,
学校[がっこう]:school, 接点[せってん]:tangent point|contact (electrical, etc.)|point of agreement
なんで 学校と接点のない人まで
then why are complete outsiders becoming unable to see her?
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
麻衣さんのことが
見えなくなったりするんだよ｡
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 学校[がっこう]:school, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 持ち出す[もちだす]:to take out/to carry out|to mention something, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
桜島先輩が 学校内の空気を
外に持ち出したのかもしれない｡
Maybe Sakurajima-senpai herself acted
as the valve that leaked the "flow" outside.
たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, 伝染[でんせん]:contagion/infection
違ったとしても 空気なんて
簡単に伝染する｡
Even if she didn't, it's everywhere around us all.
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 空気を読む[くうきをよむ]:to read the situation/to sense the mood, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|
みんな勝手に空気を読む時代だし｡
And modern society's more than happy
to go with the flow.
目に見える[めにみえる]:to be visible|clear/distinct, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
《目に見えない空気｡
The flow. Invisible, but nobody can deny its existence.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
確かに そこに存在している空気｡
戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, バカバカしい:absurd/ridiculous/silly, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
戦うなんてﾊﾞｶﾊﾞｶしい空気…》
Something that'd be entirely pointless to fight.
寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), ことができる:can (do)/to be able to (do)/can be done
(理央)寝ている間は 相手を
意識することができないからね｡
One can't be cognizant of
another person in their sleep.
意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 途切れる[とぎれる]:to pause/to be interrupted, タイミング:timing
意識が途切れたﾀｲﾐﾝｸﾞで
So the moment they fall asleep,
she becomes invisible to them.
空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 化[か]:action of making something/-ification, 現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon, 飲み込む[のみこむ]:to gulp down|to understand|to engulf||, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
空気化の現象に
飲み込まれてしまうんだろう｡
眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
眠ったら忘れる…｡
I'll forget about her if I sleep.
What are you drinking, Onii-chan?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
(かえで)お兄ちゃん
何飲んでるんですか？
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 日間[ひあい]:number of days/period of days|daily interest rate, 日間[にっかん]:daytime/during the day, 中間[ちゅうかん]:middle/midway/interim, 中間[ちゅうげん]:samurai's attendant/footman, テスト:test
明日から３日間
中間ﾃｽﾄだからな｡
An energy drink. I've got midterms for the next three days.
寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
かえでは もう寝ろ｡
You go to bed, Kaede.
I need to do this while I've still got my focus.
意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear
意識がはっきりしているうちに
やっておかないと…｡
この先[このさき]:beyond this point/from now on/after this, 記す[しるす, きす]:to write down/to note|to remember
《この先に記されていることは
Frankly, I know the following story
will be hard to believe.
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
正直 信じられないようなことだと
思うけど
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
全部 本当のことなので
必ず最後まで読むように｡
But it's all true, so make sure you read all the way to the end.
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily
必ずだ》
You have to.
しまり:closing/shutting|firmness, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
しまりのない顔ね｡
You look completely out of it.
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 美人[びじん]:beautiful woman
麻衣さんは 今日も美人ですね｡
And you look as beautiful as always.
ネクタイ:tie/necktie, 曲がる[まがる]:to bend|to turn|to be awry
ﾈｸﾀｲ曲がってる｡
Your tie's all crooked.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 新婚[しんこん]:newly-wed, プレイ:play/erotic play (esp. S&M)
まさか こんなに早く 麻衣さんと
新婚ﾌﾟﾚｲができるとは
I never thought I'd get to play newlyweds with you so soon.
顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, なさる:to do
思いませんでした｡
ﾊﾞｶは顔だけにしなさい｡
Contain the stupidity to your face.
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, カンニング:cheating, し放題[しほうだい]:having one's own way/giving free rein to one's desires/acting as one pleases
麻衣さんも 試験受けるんですか？
ｶﾝﾆﾝｸﾞし放題じゃないですか｡
You're taking the exams too?
You can cheat all you want.
勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount
そんなことしなくても私
勉強できるから｡
I don't have to cheat. I've done my homework.
答案[とうあん]:examination paper/examination script, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 紙[かみ]:paper, 紙[し]:newspaper, 配る[くばる]:to distribute/to deliver/to deal (cards), もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
でも 答案用紙
配ってもらえないんじゃ
That doesn't mean anything if they won't hand me the exam paper, though.
意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
意味ないけどね｡
But you're still going to school? How diligent.
学校[がっこう]:school, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, まじめ:diligent/serious/honest
それでも学校に行くなんて
麻衣さんは まじめだな｡
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters)
家にいても 他にすることないし｡
Well, it's not like I'd have anything to do at home.
以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting
それに 今日になったら
咲太以外の誰かに
Besides, some other people might be able to see me today.
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
見えるように
なってるかもしれないしね｡
May 27th - Day 1 of Midterms
眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|
《ﾀﾞﾒだ 眠るな…｡
No. Don't fall asleep.
If you do, you'll forget about her.
眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
眠ったら忘れる｡
Don't fall asleep!
眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|
眠るな！》
一夜漬け[いちやづけ]:last-minute cramming/overnight cramming|(vegetables) salted just overnight
梓川 その目の下のｸﾏは
一夜漬けか？
Azusagawa, what's with the bags under your eyes? Pulled an all-nighter?
双葉[ふたば]:bud/sprout
双葉…｡
ん？
Futaba...
覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
お前 覚えてるか？
は？ 何のこと？
Do you remember?
Huh? Remember what?
いや いいんだ じゃあな｡
Never mind. It's nothing.
Later.
Your hypothesis was right on the money, huh?
仮説[かせつ]:hypothesis/supposition/fictional, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
お前の仮説は正しかったわけか｡
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 燃える[もえる]:to burn/to get fired up, 展開[てんかい]:development|expansion|expansion
すげえ燃える展開だな｡
If this doesn't get me fired up, nothing will!
Is there no other way?
方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
《何か方法はないのか
何か 何か…》
Quantum Physics for Dummies
There's gotta be something!
ゾンビ:zombie, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
お前 ｿﾞﾝﾋﾞみたいになってんぞ｡
Dude, you look like a zombie.
May 28th - Day 2 of Midterms
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
何を買ったの？
What did you buy?
Oh, uh...
やっぱり:too/also|still, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
あっ え～…｡
やっぱり寝てないんだ｡
You really haven't been sleeping, huh?
座る[すわる]:to sit|to assume (a position)|to hold steady, なさる:to do, 明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 最終日[さいしゅうび]:last day/final day
ほら 座りなさい
明日が試験最終日でしょ｡
Come on. Sit down.
Tomorrow's the last day of midterms, right?
勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
勉強 見てあげるから｡
I'll tutor you.
バニーガール:bunny girl, 格好[かっこう, かっこ]:shape|appearance|state||, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
ﾊﾞﾆｰｶﾞｰﾙの格好で
教えてくれるんなら 頑張ります｡
If you teach me in your
bunny-girl outfit, I'll do my best.
脳内[のうない]:intracerebral/intracranial|intracranially, エッチ:H/h, ばっかり:only/merely|approximately
そんなことしたら 咲太の脳内は
ｴｯﾁなことばっかりになって
If I did that, your head would be too filled with dirty thoughts to study.
勉強になる[べんきょうになる]:to gain knowledge/to be illuminated|enlightening, 盲点[もうてん]:blind spot
勉強にならないでしょ｡
それは盲点だった｡
Right. I hadn't thought of that.
テスト:test, 点[ちょぼ, チョボ]:dot/point|gidayuu musicians (in kabuki), 点[てん]:spot|point|mark (e.g. in exam)||, とれる:to come off/to be removed|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear, とれる:to be photographed|to be able to photograph, 褒美[ほうび]:reward/prize, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
ﾃｽﾄで100点がとれたら
ご褒美をあげるから｡
Work hard and get a perfect score,
and I'll give you a reward.
Is this one of those "I'll do anything you want" deals?
それって
何でもしてくれるってやつ？
何でもっていっても
Yes, but there are limits.
あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
本当に 何でも
してあげるわけじゃないからね｡
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 風呂[ふろ]:bath|bathroom|room for drying lacquerware|, 我慢[がまん]:patience/endurance/perseverance
じゃあ ｢一緒にお風呂入る｣
で我慢する｡
I'll settle for just taking a bath together, then.
アウト:out, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room
ｱｳﾄよ それ｡
なら この間できなかった
That's not happening either.
Then how about we go on that
Kamakura date we missed out on last time?
鎌倉[かまくら]:Kamakura (city), デート:date/go on a date
鎌倉ﾃﾞｰﾄをするっていうのは？
いいけど…｡
Sure, but are you really okay with that?
本当に それでいいの？
You want something more extreme, huh?
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 過激[かげき]:extreme/radical, 所望[しょもう]:desire/request/wish
麻衣さんは もっと
過激なやつをご所望かぁ｡
目が覚める[めがさめる]:to awaken/to perk up/to snap out (of something)
そんなこと言ってない｡
あ～ 目が覚めるなぁ｡
I did not say anything of the sort.
Man, that really wakes me up.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 年下[としした]:younger/junior, 生意気[なまいき]:impertinent/saucy/cheeky
ﾎﾝﾄ 年下のくせに
生意気なんだから｡
For a younger boy, you really are cheeky.
現国[げんこく]:modern Japanese (esp. as a school subject), 漢字[かんじ]:Chinese characters/kanji, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
まずは現国 漢字の問題から｡
Let's start with Modern Japanese.
Nouns and verbs.
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
咲太の未来をﾎｼｮｳしてくれる人は
誰もいないの ｢ﾎｼｮｳ｣と
Classify the instances of "guarantee" from
"Nobody is willing to guarantee Sakuta's future"
老後[ろうご]:old age
咲太の老後には何のﾎｼｮｳもないの
｢ﾎｼｮｳ｣を
and "There's no guarantee
Sakuta will lead a happy retired life"
それぞれ:each/respectively, 漢字[かんじ]:Chinese characters/kanji, なさる:to do, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 文[ふみ]:letter/writings, 文[ぶん]:sentence|composition|the literary arts (as opposed to the military arts), 悪意[あくい]:ill will|bad meaning|mala fides|, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
それぞれ漢字にしなさい｡
先生 問題文に悪意を感じます｡
into "noun" or "verb."
Sensei, I sense malice emanating from the question.
書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
いいから書いて｡
Just answer it.
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come, どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
咲太の未来をﾎｼｮｳしてくれる人は
誰もいないの ｢ﾎｼｮｳ｣は どっち？
Which one is the "guarantee" from
"Nobody is willing to guarantee Sakuta's future"?
Uh...
ヒント:hint, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
え～っと…
すみません ﾋﾝﾄをください｡
Sorry. Please give me a hint.
請け負う[うけおう]:to contract/to undertake|to take over, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
こっちは請け負うって意味で
One means "to take responsibility for,"
and the other means "assurance."
守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
こっちは守るっていうような意味｡
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
ということは
麻衣さんの幸せな未来は
So the one in "I'll guarantee
Mai-san's happy future" is a verb,
僕がﾎｼｮｳしますが こっちで
and the one in "We have a guarantee
for a wonderful married life" is a noun?
将来[しょうらい]:future (usually near)/prospects, 充実[じゅうじつ]:fullness|enhancement|replenishment
２人の将来には 充実した
ﾎｼｮｳがあるは こっちってこと…｡
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 文[ふみ]:letter/writings, 文[ぶん]:sentence|composition|the literary arts (as opposed to the military arts), 変える[かえる]:to change/to alter|to reform
勝手に問題文を変えないの｡
Don't go changing the question.
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
妹さんは？
もう寝たみたいです｡
What's your sister up to?
Gone to bed already, I think.
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 一人っ子[ひとりっこ]:(an) only child, 妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend
麻衣さんは 一人っ子？
妹がいる｡
Are you an only child?
I have a younger sister.
母親[ははおや]:mother, 別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother), 父親[ちちおや]:father, 再婚[さいこん]:second marriage/remarriage, 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born
あの母親と別れた父親が
再婚してから生まれた子だけど｡
A half-sister, though. My parents divorced,
and my dad had her with his new wife.
かわいいですか？
私ほどじゃない｡
Is she cute?
Not as cute as me.
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult
うわぁ 大人げねえ｡
Wow, talk about petty.
自覚[じかく]:self-consciousness/self-awareness
自分のほうがかわいいって
自覚あるくせに
Do you like girls who praise other girls' looks
despite knowing they're the more attractive one?
別の誰かのことを
かわいい～とか言ってる女が
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to), 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear, タイプ:type/kind/sort
咲太は好きなの？
それ 嫌いなﾀｲﾌﾟ｡
Nah, I hate those types.
でしょ？
Right?
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend
だからって 妹さんまで…｡
But come on. She's your sister.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 効く[きく]:to be effective|to do its work|to be possible to use, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
よかった
ちゃんと効いたみたいね｡
Good.
I'm glad they worked.
眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|
僕は まだ眠るわけには…｡
I can't go to sleep yet.
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
咲太は よく頑張ったわ｡
You did great, Sakuta.
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
私のために頑張ってくれた｡
You tried so hard for me.
まだまだ:still some way to go before the goal/still more to come/much more
違う まだまだ こんなんじゃ…｡
No... I'm not done yet.
十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly
だから もう十分 もういいから｡
You've done more than enough. You can rest now.
よくない…｡
No... I can't.
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, ひとり:one person|alone/unmarried, ひとり:incense burner|utensil for carrying live charcoal
もともと私は
ひとりだったんだから 大丈夫よ｡
I've always been alone anyway.
I'll be fine.
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
咲太に忘れられるくらい
何でもない｡
It won't bother me one bit if you forget about me.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
それでも 今日までありがとう｡
But still, thanks for everything.
それと ごめんね｡
And I'm sorry.
おやすみ:holiday/day off|sleep
おやすみ 咲太｡
Good night, Sakuta.
さよなら:good-bye
さよなら｡
And goodbye.
Teenage Pig Doesn't
Dream of Bunny Girls
...chan! Onii-chan! Wake up!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
(かえで)お兄ちゃん 朝です｡
Isn't today the last day of midterms?
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 遅刻[ちこく]:lateness/late coming
今日まで試験ですよね？
遅刻しますよ？
Do you want to be late?
You're a lifesaver, Kaede.
助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
ああ 助かったよ かえで
起こしてくれて ありがとう｡
Thanks for waking me up.
こ これは何ですか？
Wh-What is this?
I bought it for you to wear, I guess?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 着せる[きせる]:to put clothes on (someone)|to plate|to accuse (of some crime)
かえでに着せようと
思ったのかな？
N-No way!
着る[きる]:to wear (in modern Japanese, from the shoulders down)/to put on|to bear (guilt, etc.), セクシー:sexy, 路線[ろせん]:route/line/alignment, 服[ふく]:clothes (esp. Western clothes)|counter for doses of medicine, gulps of tea, drags of a cigarette, etc., 服[ぶく]:mourning clothes|mourning/period of mourning
き 着ません！
こういうｾｸｼｰ路線の服は
I'm not ready to wear such sexy outfits yet!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
かえでには まだ早いです！
May 29th
"Frankly, I know the following story will be hard to believe.
この先[このさき]:beyond this point/from now on/after this, 記す[しるす, きす]:to write down/to note|to remember
｢この先に記されていることは
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
正直 信じられないようなことだと
思うけど
But it's all true, so make sure you read all the way to the end.
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
全部 本当のことなので
必ず最後まで読むように｡
You have to."
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily
必ずだ｣｡
なんだ これ？
What is this?
"May 6th.
野生[やせい]:wild/growing wild|I, バニーガール:bunny girl, 出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
｢５月６日
野生のﾊﾞﾆｰｶﾞｰﾙに出会った｡
I ran into a bunny girl in the wild.
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 峰ヶ[みね]:peak/summit|back of a blade, 原[げん]:original/primitive/primary, 高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
その正体は 峰ヶ原高校の
３年の先輩
It was a student at Minegahara High,
one year my senior.
The celebrity..."
有名人[ゆうめいじん]:celebrity/public figure/big name
あの有名人… だ｣｡
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 歴史[れきし]:history
僕の黒歴史というやつか｡
What is this, an old creative writing exercise?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 大垣[おおがき]:roofed mud wall around a villa or temple
《確かに 大垣には行ったけど
Yeah, I did go to Ogaki,
but wasn't that just a solo trip?
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 旅[たび]:travel/trip/journey, 旅[りょ]:500-man battalion (Zhou-dynasty Chinese army)
あれは ただの一人旅だったよな》
We were both tired, so
Mai-san used the shower...
...sound of the shower alone...
...called on the phone...
We were both silent for a while.
"Hey, want to kiss?"
Mai-san asked suddenly.
I thought for a moment.
-
san
埋める[うずめる]:to cover/to bury (e.g. one's face in hands)|to fill (completely), 埋める[うめる]:to bury (e.g. in the ground)|to fill up (e.g. audience fills a hall)|to plug (a gap)||
彼女ができたら
埋めろってことか？
Am I supposed to fill in the blanks
once I get a girlfriend?
You look a lot better today.
だいぶ:lengthy (of a book, etc.)/voluminous|most (e.g. most part), だいぶ:considerably/greatly/a lot, 顔色[かおいろ, がんしょく]:complexion/one's colour|countenance
今日は だいぶ顔色がいいな｡
あ？
You were like a zombie the last couple days.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, ゾンビ:zombie, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
昨日までは
ｿﾞﾝﾋﾞみたいな顔してたろ｡
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 一夜漬け[いちやづけ]:last-minute cramming/overnight cramming|(vegetables) salted just overnight, タイプ:type/kind/sort
咲太って 試験前に一夜漬けとか
するﾀｲﾌﾟだったっけ？
Were you always the type to pull all-nighters before exams?
諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to), 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, タイプ:type/kind/sort
いや 諦めて さっさと寝るﾀｲﾌﾟ｡
だよな｡
Nah. I'm the type to throw in the towel and go to sleep.
Figures.
What's up?
視線[しせん]:one's line of sight/one's gaze/one's eyes (looking), 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
どした？
いや 視線を感じたっていうか…｡
Well...
It felt like someone was staring at me.
Hey.
おう｡
これ｡
Here.
A love letter?
レター:letter
ﾗﾌﾞなﾚﾀｰ？
違うよ｡
Hell no.
あらゆる:all/every, 物質[ぶっしつ]:material/substance|matter, 観測[かんそく]:observation/survey/measurement
｢あらゆる物質は
誰かに観測されることで
"Assumption: all things and states are only determined to exist when they're observed."
この世[このよ]:this world/the present life (in contrast to the land of the dead), 物質[ぶっしつ]:material/substance|matter, 形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin, 確定[かくてい]:decision/settlement|definition, 仮定[かてい]:assumption/supposition/hypothesis
この世に物質としての形が
確定すると仮定する｣｡
こりゃ:hey there/I say/see here
なんだ こりゃ？
私にも わかんない｡
The heck is this?
I have no idea either.
教科書[きょうかしょ]:textbook/coursebook/schoolbook, 挟まる[はさまる]:to get between/to be caught in, 今朝[けさ, こんちょう]:this morning, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
教科書に挟まってて
今朝 気づいた｡
I found it in my textbook this morning.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
これと一緒に｡
Along with this note.
Give this letter
to Azusagawa
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over
じゃ 確かに渡したからね｡
Well, my job here is done.
消滅[しょうめつ]:extinction/extinguishment|annihilation, 全校[ぜんこう]:the whole school, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, 無自覚[むじかく]:unaware or unmindful of/unconsciousness, 無視[むし]:disregarding/ignoring
｢…の消滅が 全校生徒の
無自覚な無視に
"If blank's disappearance is caused by the student body's subconscious ignoring of her,
起因[きいん]:cause/origin, 上回る[うわまわる]:to exceed (esp. figures: profits, unemployment rate, etc.)/to surpass/to be more than, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
起因するのであれば
それを上回る存在理由を
then Azusagawa just needs to give her a different purpose in their heads.
作り出す[つくりだす]:to manufacture/to produce|to invent
梓川が作り出せばいい｡
In other words, his love just needs to overwrite their cognizance, or lack thereof."
全校[ぜんこう]:the whole school, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, 無意識[むいしき]:unconsciousness|the unconscious
つまり 全校生徒の無意識を
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 上回る[うわまわる]:to exceed (esp. figures: profits, unemployment rate, etc.)/to surpass/to be more than, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
梓川の愛が
上回ればいいという話だ｣｡
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛ねぇ…｡
Love, huh?
High
School
Second
Year
Modern
Japanese
Exam
High
School
Second
Year
Modern
Japanese
Exam
2. Classify the following
words as either noun or verb.
Guarantee (noun)
Guarantee (verb)
請け負う[うけおう]:to contract/to undertake|to take over, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
⦅こっちは請け負うって意味で
One means "to take responsibility for,"
and the other means "assurance."
守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
こっちは守るっていうような意味｡
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
咲太の未来をﾎｼｮｳしてくれる人は
誰もいないの ｢ﾎｼｮｳ｣と
Classify the instances of "guarantee" from
"Nobody is willing to guarantee Sakuta's future"
老後[ろうご]:old age
咲太の老後には何のﾎｼｮｳもないの
｢ﾎｼｮｳ｣を
and "There's no guarantee
Sakuta will lead a happy retired life"
それぞれ:each/respectively, 漢字[かんじ]:Chinese characters/kanji, なさる:to do
それぞれ漢字にしなさい⦆
into "noun" or "verb."
あれ？
Huh?
梓川 どうした？
What's the matter, Azusagawa?
Number two!
大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||
大のほうです！
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
《大事なことを思い出した｡
I've remembered something important:
大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, よみがえる:to be resurrected/to be resuscitated|to be recalled (e.g. memories)
大切な人の記憶がよみがえった｡
the memories of someone dear to me.
相手をする[あいてをする]:to keep company/to look after/to entertain, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
これから僕が相手をするのは
空気だ｡
What I'm going to be fighting now is the flow.
押す[おす]:to push|to apply pressure from above|to stamp (i.e. a passport)||, 引く[ひく]:to pull|to draw (attention, etc.)|to draw back||, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
押しても引いても叩いても
何もない あの空気｡
The flow you can't pull, push, or hit.
学校[がっこう]:school, 取り巻く[とりまく]:to surround/to circle/to enclose, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
学校を取り巻く空気｡
The flow coursing all through this school.
Living life going with the flow is easy.
右[みぎ]:right/right hand side|afore-mentioned (esp. in vertical Japanese writing), ならう:to take lessons in/to be taught/to learn (from a teacher), ならう:to imitate/to follow/to emulate, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 楽[らく]:comfort/ease|raku pottery
右にならえの行き方は楽でいい｡
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 判断[はんだん]:judgment|divination|judgement, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole
悪いことの判断を
全部自分でするのは
Thinking for yourself about what's right and wrong takes energy,
カロリー:calorie
ｶﾛﾘｰを使うし
and you can get hurt if you have views of your own that are rejected.
意思[いし]:intention/wish/purpose, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 否定[ひてい]:negation/denial|NOT operation
自分の意思を持つと
否定されたときに
傷つく[きずつく]:to be wounded|to get hurt feelings|to get damaged, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
傷つくことになる｡
On the other hand, following the herd gives you safety and security.
点[ちょぼ, チョボ]:dot/point|gidayuu musicians (in kabuki), 点[てん]:spot|point|mark (e.g. in exam)||, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security
その点 みんなと一緒であれば
安心安全でいられる｡
見たくないものを見ずにいられる｡
You can be blind to things you don't want to see,
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
考えたくないことを
考えずにいられる｡
ignorant to things you don't want to think about.
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, ひと事[ひとごと, たにんごと]:other people's affairs/somebody else's problem, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
全部 ひと事で済ませられる｡
You can sweep it all under the rug.
だけど… みんながそうしてるから
ってだけで
But everyone else doing it
doesn't justify hurting someone.
苦しめる[くるしめる]:to torment/to pain|to harass, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 理屈[りくつ]:theory/reason
誰かを苦しめていいなんて
理屈はない｡
Everyone else saying or doing something doesn't make it right.
みんながそうしてるから
みんながそう言ってるから
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 限る[かぎる]:to restrict/to limit|to be restricted to
それが正しいとも限らない｡
だいたい:outline/main point|general, だいたい:battalion
だいたい ｢みんな｣って 誰だ？
Who is "everyone," anyway?
Kanagawa Prefectural Minegahara High School
年下[としした]:younger/junior, 扱い[あつかい]:treatment/service, からかう:to ridicule/to tease/to mock
いつも僕を年下扱いで
からかってきた彼女｡
She always plays the
older-girl card to mess with me.
色気[いろけ]:colouring|sex appeal (esp. women)|romance|, 自爆[じばく]:suicide bombing (e.g. crashing one's plane into a target)/self-destruction/blowing oneself up, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 真っ赤[まっか]:bright red/deep red|downright (e.g. lie), してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
お色気ﾈﾀで自爆して
顔を真っ赤にしていた彼女｡
She always digs her own grave with dirty talk
and leaves herself red-faced.
失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder, 隠す[かくす]:to hide/to conceal, 意地[いじ]:stubbornness|disposition|appetite
その失敗を隠そうとして
意地になって強がってた彼女｡
And then, she gets all stubborn
and tries to hide her embarrassment.
わがまま:selfishness/egoism|disobedience, 女王[じょおう]:queen, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 気分屋[きぶんや]:moody person
わがままで 女王様で 気分屋で
She's selfish, bossy, capricious,
意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 年上[としうえ]:older/senior, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
そのくせ意外とうぶだった
一つ年上の先輩｡
and surprisingly naïve for a girl
who's a year older than me.
無視[むし]:disregarding/ignoring, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
もう無視なんかさせない｡
I won't let you guys ignore her anymore. I won't let you turn a blind eye.
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
見て見ぬふりなんかさせない｡
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 刻みつける[きざみつける]:to engrave/to carve out
できないくらいに みんなの記憶に
刻みつけてやる！》
I'm going to etch her into your memories so vividly that you won't be able to!
空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
もう空気なんて読んでやるか｡
I'm done going with the flow. Screw that!
バカバカしい:absurd/ridiculous/silly
ﾊﾞｶﾊﾞｶしい！
いいか お前ら よく聞け！
Listen up well, you jerks!
I'm Azusagawa Sakuta, roll number 1 in class 2-1,
組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting, 出席[しゅっせき]:attendance/presence|to attend, 番号[ばんごう]:number/series of digits, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
２年１組の出席番号１番
梓川咲太は
組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting, 桜[さくら, サクラ]:cherry tree|decoy|hired applauder|, 島[しま]:island|territory (of a prostitute, organized crime gang, etc.)/turf, 島[とう]:Island|insula/island, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
３年１組の
桜島麻衣先輩のことが…｡
and Sakurajima Mai of class 3-1...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ﾊｧ… 桜島先輩のことが
is the one I love!
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
好きだ～!!
I love Sakurajima-senpai!
やっぱり:too/also|still
あ～ ｸｿ やっぱり こうなるのか｡
Shit! I should've known this would happen!
恥[はじ, じょく]:shame/embarrassment/disgrace, 損[そん]:loss/damage|disadvantage, ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
恥のかき損だよ ったく｡
I embarrassed myself for nothing!
空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.)
これだから空気となんか
戦いたくなかったんだ｡
This is why I didn't want to fight the flow!
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
ﾁｸｼｮｰ！ 麻衣さん 好きだ！
Damn it all!
Mai-san, I love you!
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
好きだ 好きだ 好きだ
好きだ 好きだ～!!
I love, love, love, love, love you!
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
麻衣さん 好きだ！
Mai-san, I love you!
I want to hold hands and walk down Shichirigahama Beach with you!
手をつなぐ[てをつなぐ]:to join hands (with), 歩く[あるく]:to walk
手をつないで
七里ヶ浜を歩きたい！
バニーガール:bunny girl, 格好[かっこう, かっこ]:shape|appearance|state||, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree
ﾊﾞﾆｰｶﾞｰﾙの格好だって
もう一度見たい！
I want to see you as a bunny girl again!
抱きしめる[だきしめる]:to hug someone close/to hold someone tight/to embrace closely
ぎゅっと抱きしめてみたいし
I want to hold you tight,
ｷｽだってしたいんだ！
and I want to kiss you too!
ﾊｧ ﾊｧ…｡
要する[ようする]:to need/to demand/to take, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe
要するにさぁ 麻衣さん
Long story short, Mai-san!
大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
大 大 大 大 大好きだ～!!
I super-duper-ultra-giga love you!
ﾊｧ ﾊｧ…｡
You don't have to yell like a madman. I can hear you.
大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 声[こえ]:voice, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
そんなに大きな声で
言われなくても 聞こえてる｡
近所[きんじょ]:neighbourhood/neighborhood, 迷惑[めいわく, べいこく]:trouble/bother/annoyance
近所迷惑でしょ｡
You're being a nuisance, you know.
I figured I might as well let everyone around the world know.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 世界中[せかいじゅう]:around the world/throughout the world, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
どうせだから 世界中の人に
知ってもらおうと思って｡
ﾊﾞｶなんだから｡
You're such an idiot.
賢い[かしこい]:wise/clever/smart
賢いふりしてるやつよりは
いいでしょ｡
Better to be an idiot than someone pretending to be smart, right?
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ﾎﾝﾄ ﾊﾞｶ｡
A complete and utter fool!
Doing this will only make people
spread weird rumors about you again!
目立つ[めだつ]:to be conspicuous/to stand out, うわさ:rumour/rumor/report, 立つ[たつ]:to stand|to find oneself (e.g. in a difficult position)|to depart (on a plane, train, etc.)
こんなことして目立ったら
またﾍﾝなうわさが立つわよ｡
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, うわさ:rumour/rumor/report, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 歓迎[かんげい]:welcome/reception
麻衣さんとうわさされるなら
大歓迎｡
I'd be perfectly fine with a few rumors about you and me.
そうじゃなくて…｡
That's not the point.
ﾊﾞｶ… ﾊﾞｶ咲太｡
You idiot.
Sakuta, you idiot.
ｲｯ… えっ なんで？
What? Why?
You liar! You said you wouldn't forget!
ウソつき:liar (sometimes said with not much seriousness)/fibber, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
ｳｿつき 忘れないって
言ったじゃない！
You said you'd never forget!
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
絶対に忘れないって｡
ごめん…｡
Sorry.
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
許さない｡
ごめん…｡
I won't forgive you.
I'm sorry.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
絶対に許さない｡
I'll never forgive you.
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, 離す[はなす]:to separate/to part/to divide
じゃあ 許してくれるまで
離さない｡
I won't let you go until you do.
一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
だったら 一生許さない｡
Then I won't for the rest of my life.
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant
え～｡
なによ 嫌なの？
Huh?
What, do you have a problem with that?
私に ここまで言わせておいて…｡
After all you're making me say?
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.)
あの… 足｡
Uh...
Your foot...
踏む[ふむ]:to step on|to experience|to estimate||, うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant, なさる:to do
踏まれて うれしいんでしょ？
ごめん ごめんなさい｡
Aren't you happy I'm stepping on you?
Sorry. I'm sorry.
It won't happen again, so please forgive me.
反省[はんせい]:reflection/reconsideration|regret, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
反省しているので
許してください｡
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 踏む[ふむ]:to step on|to experience|to estimate||, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck
他に言うことは？
踏んでもらえて幸せです｡
Anything else?
I feel very fortunate to have you step on me.
言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech
今 私が聞きたいのは
そんな言葉じゃない｡
That's not what I want to hear right now.
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
好きです…｡
I like you.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ﾎﾝﾄに？
Really?
Not really.
大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
ｳｿです 大好きです｡
I love you.
ねぇ 咲太｡
なに？
Hey, Sakuta.
What?
か月[かげつ]:months (period of), 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree
今の １か月後に
もう一度言って｡
Say that again one month from now.
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response
なんで？
ここで返事すると
Why?
If I gave you an answer now, I'd feel like I got carried away in the heat of the moment.
勢い[いきおい]:force|influence|impetus|, 雰囲気[ふんいき, ふいんき]:mood|a certain air|air, 押し切る[おしきる]:to face down the opposition/to overcome resistance|to press and cut, 感じがする[かんじがする]:to have a feeling (that)/to have a sensation (that)
勢いと雰囲気で
押し切られた感じがする｡
場[ば]:place|field|occasion||, 場[じょう]:place/spot/grounds, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
僕としては この場で
ｷｽくらいまでしたいんだけど｡
Personally, I'd like to kiss you right here and now.
ドキドキ:thump-thump/bang-bang/pit-a-pat
今ﾄﾞｷﾄﾞｷしてるのも
Maybe my heart is only beating so fast right now
in the heat of the moment, too.
状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
こういう状況だからかも
しれないし｡
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising, 冷静[れいせい]:calm/composure/coolness
麻衣さん 意外と冷静だね｡
You're awfully calm and collected about this.
か月[かげつ]:months (period of), 待つ[まつ]:to wait|to await|to depend on, 毎日[まいにち]:every day
じゃあ １か月待てないから
毎日言ってもいい？
Well, I can't wait a month, so can I say it every day?
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, か月[かげつ]:months (period of), 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on, なさる:to do
いいけど｡ ちゃんと
１か月続けなさいよ｡
Sure, but you'd better keep it up
for the whole month.
気が変わる[きがかわる]:to change one's mind, たんだ:base hit/one-base hit/single, たんだ:chopping|base hit/one-base hit
できなかったら
気が変わったんだと見なすから｡
If you don't, I'll assume that you changed your mind.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 空気を読む[くうきをよむ]:to read the situation/to sense the mood, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
みんな ﾎﾝﾄ
空気を読むのが好きよね｡
People sure do love going with the flow.
同級生[どうきゅうせい]:classmate, 病院[びょういん]:hospital, 送り[おくり]:seeing off|funeral|escapement, うわさ:rumour/rumor/report
咲太が同級生を
病院送りにしたっていううわさ
You know that rumor about Sakuta
sending his classmates to the hospital?
デタラメ:irresponsible utterance/nonsense/bullshit
あれ ﾃﾞﾀﾗﾒだから！
It's complete hogwash!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
なんで桜島先輩
そんなの知ってんだ？
Why does Sakurajima-senpai know about that?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
てか ２人は どういう関係？
What's their deal, anyway?
みんなに
言ってほしかったんでしょ？
There. I told them like you wanted.
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 注目[ちゅうもく]:notice/attention/observation
麻衣さんのせいで
すげえ注目されてる｡
Thanks to you, I'm the center of attention now.
職員室[しょくいんしつ]:staff room, 説教[せっきょう]:propounding/preaching|remonstration, 憂鬱[ゆううつ]:depression/melancholy/dejection
職員室でお説教とか 憂鬱だな｡
Am I going to get lectured in the staff room? Boy, will that suck.
いいじゃない｡
Hey, no big deal.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
私も一緒に怒られてあげるから｡
I'll be there to get yelled at with you.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
まっ それなら悪くないか｡
I guess that doesn't sound too bad.
そこの２人 ちょっと来い！
You two over there!
Come with me!
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 桜[さくら, サクラ]:cherry tree|decoy|hired applauder|, 島[しま]:island|territory (of a prostitute, organized crime gang, etc.)/turf, 島[とう]:Island|insula/island, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 取り戻す[とりもどす]:to take back/to regain/to get back
《こうして世界は
桜島麻衣を取り戻した》
And so, Sakurajima Mai once again became a part of our world.
June 2nd
やっぱ:too/also|still, 心臓[しんぞう]:heart|guts|central part, 鉄[かね, かな]:money|metal, 鉄[てつ]:iron (Fe)|strong and hard (as iron)|railway|
やっぱ 咲太の心臓って
鉄でできてんだな｡
Your heart's gotta be made of steel, Sakuta.
恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful
私だったら恥ずかしくて死んでる｡
I would've died of embarrassment by now.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 青春[せいしゅん]:youth/springtime of life/adolescent
さすが梓川 青春ﾌﾞﾀ野郎だね｡
But that's our Azusagawa.
The most teenage of teenage pigs.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
それ どういう意味だよ｡
What's that supposed to mean?
When rumors of the hospitalization incident spread all around school,
病院[びょういん]:hospital, 送り[おくり]:seeing off|funeral|escapement, うわさ:rumour/rumor/report, 学校[がっこう]:school, 流れる[ながれる]:to stream|to be washed away|to drift||
病院送りのうわさが
学校中に流れたとき
空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, バカバカしい:absurd/ridiculous/silly
空気と戦うなんて
ﾊﾞｶﾊﾞｶしいとか言ってたの
you said it'd be entirely pointless to fight the flow, remember?
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
忘れた？
言ってたな｡
He totally did.
本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth
自分のためには
本気になれなかったくせに
You couldn't lift a finger for your own sake,
美人[びじん]:beautiful woman, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 恥[はじ, じょく]:shame/embarrassment/disgrace, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
美人の先輩のためになら
どんな恥もかけるなんてやつが
but you were willing to make a spectacle out of yourself for a hot older girl.
青春[せいしゅん]:youth/springtime of life/adolescent
青春ﾌﾞﾀ野郎じゃなくて 何なのよ｡
What does that make you
if not a total teenage pig?
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 双葉[ふたば]:bud/sprout, 仮説[かせつ]:hypothesis/supposition/fictional, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
なぁ 結局 双葉の仮説が
正しかったってことでいいのか？
So in the end, was your hypothesis proven right?
思春期[ししゅんき]:puberty, 不安定[ふあんてい]:instability/insecurity/crankiness, 精神[せいしん]:mind/soul/heart
さあね 思春期の不安定な精神や
Who knows?
If the illusions caused by teenage instability and warped worldview
強烈[きょうれつ]:strong/intense/severe, 思い込み[おもいこみ]:wrong impression/subjective impression/assumption, 見せる[みせる]:to show/to display, まやかし:deception/make-believe/fake
強烈な思い込みが見せるまやかし｡
思春期[ししゅんき]:puberty, 症候[しょうこう]:symptoms, 群[ぐん]:group/bunch|group, 群[むら]:gathering
そういうのが思春期症候群だって
いうなら
are what you call Puberty Syndrome,
科学的[かがくてき]:scientific, 検証[けんしょう]:verification/inspection, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
科学的な検証なんて
あてにならないよ｡
then the scientific method
isn't going to help with that.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
まぁ でも 私たちの世界なんて
But, hey, maybe our world is so simple
that a mere confession can turn it on its head.
告白[こくはく]:confession|profession of love|confession of sins (e.g. the confessional), 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
告白ひとつで
ｶﾞﾗｯと変わってしまうくらいに
単純[たんじゅん]:simplicity/simple/uncomplicated
単純なのかもね｡
証明[しょうめい]:proof/verification/certification
梓川が証明したようにさ｡
As you proved.
そうかもな｡
Yeah, maybe.
But that wasn't to be the last incident related to Puberty Syndrome.
After Schrödinger's cat
came Laplace's demon, or well,
思春期[ししゅんき]:puberty, 症候群[しょうこうぐん]:syndrome, まつわる:to coil around/to follow about|to be related to, 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident
《だけど 思春期症候群に
まつわる事件は
終わり[おわり]:the end
これで終わりじゃなかった｡
Laplace's little devil.
猫[ねこ, ネコ]:cat|shamisen|geisha||, 猫[ねこま]:cat, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 悪魔[あくま]:devil|Satan|Māra
ｼｭﾚﾃﾞｨﾝｶﾞｰの猫の次は
ﾗﾌﾟﾗｽの悪魔
That's my Senpai. A total pig.
現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
いや ﾗﾌﾟﾗｽのﾌﾟﾁﾃﾞﾋﾞﾙが現れたんだ》
Next Episode
#4: No Tomorrow for Pigs